Hi everyone, it's Dr.
Donna McMahon and I am
presenting to you today
Pediatric Pulmonary Disease
Parts 1 and 2. This is
part of your PPOM 2 course
and you will notice that I
will be wearing different
outfits, will be in
different rooms because
I am recording this in
several parts, so welcome.
Let's take a look at the
session objectives. One, to
understand the epidemiology,
pathophysiology, and clinical
presentation of cystic
fibrosis, asthma, pneumonia,
and bronchiolitis. To
distinguish between multiple
causes of respiratory distress
in the newborn, including
transient tachypnea of
the newborn and meconium
aspiration syndrome. Identify
radiographic differences
between common respiratory
pathologies to distinguish
between multiple causes of
pediatric upper airway disease,
including epiglottitis,
retropharyngeal abscesses,
and peritonsillar abscesses.
In addition, to understand
social factors in pediatric
pulmonology, including
environmental health, as well
as vaccine non-adherence.
Case number one. A 15-month
-old toddler presents to
your office for the first
time, and mom complains that
there's a wet cough, and
it's been around for a while.
He has a history of
recurrent pneumonia,
one episode required
hospitalization, and she
reports he seems to
be small for his age,
bowel movements sometimes
smell really bad.
Patient was adopted and
the birth history is
unremarkable and we
don't know anything about
the biological parents.
He lives with his adoptive
parents in a home that
was built in 2002.
Let's look at his
physical examination. He's
ill-appearing. He has a
frequent moist cough, and
he seems to be small for
age. He has an elevated
temperature at 100.5
degrees Fahrenheit,
elevated heart rate at 166
beats a minute, elevated
respiratory rate at
45 breaths per minute.
His height and his head
circumference are at the
20th percentile, and his
weight is at the 10th
percentile. His cardiac
evaluation reveals a positive
S1 and S2 with no murmurs,
rubs, or gallops. And
his respiratory exam reveals
pursed lips with wheeze
and ronchi in all lung
fields on auscultation.
So what's your
diagnosis? Asthma, cystic
fibrosis, foreign
body aspiration,
bronchiolitis,
or laryngotracheobronchitis.
If you chose cystic
fibrosis, you are correct.
Let's talk about the
epidemiology. It's an
autosomal recessive
disorder that results in a
shorter lifespan, but we'll
talk a little bit more
about that later. Over
70,000 individuals are
affected worldwide. It
occurs in predominantly
people of European
descent, but all
races and ethnicities
have been affected.
It involves the long
arm of chromosome 7.
Chromosome 7 includes
the cystic fibrosis
transmembrane regulator,
and that's a chloride
channel that's located
on the apical surfaces
of epithelial cells.
So in essence, it
regulates the water and
salt across membranes.
most common mutation is
the the deletion of three
base pairs at the 508
position which results
in an absence of phenylalanine
and what the heck
does that mean well it
means that it messes up
that water and salt
regulation across membranes
let's talk about the pathogenesis
and this is discussed
also in the cystic fibrosis
brick the epithelial
cells in the airways
have a reduced ability to
secrete chloride which causes
the airway epithelium to
reabsorb excessive sodium
and therefore water back
into the cell which leads
to dehydration of the
airway secretions and then
it's difficult to clear those
secretions which leads
to colonizing of bacteria
especially Staph aureus
and Pseudomonas aeruginosa.
In the sweat glands and
you can see here on the
slide that would be the
upper section of the
picture. The chloride can't
be reabsorbed back into
the cell. Sodium follows
chloride, and it remains
in the lumen of the sweat
ducts. And actually,
if you lick the skin on
a baby who has cystic
fibrosis, they will
taste salty. And
that's actually how
they diagnosed children
many many many years
ago by licking them you
clinical signs and symptoms
the gi tract of the
neonate malabsorption
especially fat malabsorption
sugars and proteins
less so this leads to
failure to thrive
steatoria and liver disease
Pulmonary problems,
chronic cough,
respiratory infections,
nasal polyps,
recurrent sinusitis,
recurrent infections,
and pneumonia.
Other problems,
fat-soluble vitamin
deficiency because of that
malabsorption problem. There's
something called CF-related
diabetes, infertility,
electrolyte disturbances,
later on digital
clubbing, and you can have
congenital absence
of the vas deferens.
How is CF diagnosed?
Well newborn screening
is done in all 50 states.
If there it comes up
positive then that generates
another test and then that's
positive that generates
another test. The gold standard
for diagnosis is a sweat
chloride test and that is
talked about in your BRIC.
And then there are
criteria for diagnosis.
Clinical features and two
abnormal sweat chloride
tests or two known
mutations or an abnormal
nasal epithelial potential
difference. That is
something I have not seen
performed on any patients.
Anyone notice that I have
a different shirt on?
What are some indications
for sweat chloride
testing? We have
respiratory gastrointestinal
and then the miscellaneous
column. For respiratory,
if you have a patient
who has a chronic
or recurring cough,
recurrent bronchiolitis,
a recurrent or difficult
to control wheezing
or asthma, and an
unexplained respiratory
infection caused by
Pseudomonas aeruginosa, that
can be an indication
to sweat the patient.
Gastrointestinal,
meconium ileus,
neonatal intestinal
obstruction,
steatorrhea, and
malabsorption, along with,
like we said before, a
positive newborn screen,
patient has digital
clubbing, failure
to thrive, or a family history.
For the management of CF,
we can look at the different
systems that the disease
affects. So in respiratory,
what do we want to do?
We want to clear airway
secretions. We do that
with chest physiotherapy,
OMM, aerosolized DNase,
and infection control
with aggressive antibiotic
therapy. If there's
pancreatic insufficiency,
we supplement with
enzyme capsules and then
fat-soluble vitamins.
For meconium ileus, we utilize
enemas. For CF
-related diabetes,
we utilize insulin. For
cholestasis, we
utilize that drug.
So even well-controlled
patients have a long problem
list. You see the different
systems. In 2019, the FDA
approved a CFTR gene modulator
for older kids and young
adults, and it has improved
overall symptoms because
it's changing the gene
mutation and it's been a game
changer for some if they
if it hits that targeted
gene. Studies are ongoing
for younger kids to utilize
these gene modulators and
drug companies are working on
different modulators and
so that may be our future.
What's the prognosis
for cystic fibrosis,
it improves every year.
Don't restrict the
patient's activity. We
have increasing life
expectancy and improved
quality of life.
We have now across
the United States
multidisciplinary care in
cystic fibrosis centers.
Transition to adult
care, which was very rare
in the past, is now
much more common and
internists and pulmonologists
are much more well
-versed to handle cystic
fibrosis patients.
Case number two, a nine
-year-old presents to the
emergency department
with his parents with a
complaint of a 10-hour
history of wheezing and
shortness of breath. The
mother states that about
for the past three to
four days he's had a bad
cold And he was given
one albuterol nebulizer
treatment at home one hour
ago with no improvement.
Physical examination.
The patient
is ill-appearing, in distress,
seated upright, hands on knees,
leaning forward. Vital signs,
temperature is elevated
at 99 degrees Fahrenheit,
heart rate 124, blood
pressure 128 over 94,
respiratory rate 38,
with a pulse oximeter
reading of 90% on room
air, which is decreased.
The sternocleidomastoid
muscles appear hypertonic
bilaterally, and a
wheeze is appreciated on
exhalation in all lung
fields. with some slight upper
lobe inspiratory crackles.
On cardiac exam, there's
an S1 and S2, but like we
said before, an increased
heart rate with no
murmurs, rubs, or gallops.
What do you think
the diagnosis is for
this patient?
Bronchiolitis, pneumonia,
asthma,
allergic rhinitis.
If you chose asthma,
you are correct.
You've discussed
asthma in the adult
population, and today
we'll discuss it
concerning the
pediatric population.
Asthma is defined as
an episodic airway
hyperreactivity, and that's
typically due to allergens,
irritants, infection.
Exercise can be due to
stress and it's typically
reversible. You can have
permanent airway remodeling
and this is due to
vascular hyperplasia and
increased extracellular
matrix proteins that are
that come into the area
and this leads to decreased
pulmonary function.
I've included only
as a review from what
you have learned in
your foundational
courses about the
immunology of asthma.
I think it's a nice pictorial
of everything that's going on.
Have you noticed that I
have different glasses?
And it's cold in here,
so I have my lab coat
on. Let's talk about the
epidemiology. Our latest
statistics come from the
CDC released in 2021.
Almost 5 million
children in the United
States are considered
to have asthma.
In childhood,
it's boys more than girls,
and then that switches
in adulthood, where
it's more females than
males. It's approximately
8% of the population.
over the past 20 years we've
had many more emergency
room visits hospitalizations
and deaths especially
in black children and why
is that what we'll look
at the bait breakdown in
another slide but is it
health inequity is it just
innate more severe disease
in certain populations um
is it the environment of
particular populations I
think it's multi-factorial
but we really have to
look at health inequities
there's a higher incidence
of asthma in metropolitan
areas and why is that
more trucks more cars more
pollution perhaps with
electric vehicles that will
change in the future
more dust more dust mites
more rodent dander all
those sorts of nice things
it seems to be more in
affluent nation nations and
if you have an allergic
condition and if you look
below strongest risk
factors atopi or family
history so if you have
these allergic conditions,
more likely that you will
be diagnosed with asthma.
This is the slide talking
about asthma prevalence
by race and ethnicity for
kids under the age of 18.
This is the CDC and keep
in mind that of all kids
with asthma, 33% are at or
below the poverty level,
the federal poverty level.
So when we look at major
groups, and this certainly
doesn't add up to 100%,
but we're looking at some
more common groups, white
non-Hispanic, almost 8% of
the population for kids.
Black non-Hispanic almost
11% American Indian and
Alaska Native 12% Asian non
-Hispanic 4% and generalized
Hispanic not breaking it
down about 6% just to give
you an idea of there there
are differences between these
groups and to think about
why are there differences
New York State we have this
is from 2016 I think it's
fairly accurate you look at
how many cases throughout
New York State my office
is covering up the five
boroughs of Manhattan but
they are in the darkest blue
area and then Nassau and
Suffolk County on Long Island
where I am sitting right
now is just one step below.
So if you look at the
highest incident, it's in the
Bronx, Kings County, New
York City, Queens, Richmond.
Let's take a look at Arkansas.
This is out of a journal
article from 2010, the
Annals of Allergy, Asthma,
and Immunology, a well
-regarded journal. Even
though it's old data, I
think it gives us a good
sense of what's going on.
So if we look at kids
that are screened,
this is my takeaway,
you look at the total
population screened
About 28% of kids who
live in rural Arkansas are
at risk of asthma and
urban about 24% of the kids
screened that lived in an
urban area are at risk.
It's pretty significant.
Asthma severity in at
-risk urban and rural
children, mild asthma
tends to have a higher
chance of having mild
asthma if you live in urban
areas and you have a
higher risk of having
moderate to severe asthma
in the rural areas.
let's return to the
patient so the patient is
administered a nebulized
treatment of albuterol and
ipratropium bromide atrovent
three hours later during
this treatment things happen
let's repeat his vital
signs his temperature is
98.8 heart rate came down
to 90 respiratory rate
down to 20. And his pulse
oximetry on room air went
up to 98%. When you ask a
more detailed history, the
patient and his mom admit
that he has shortness of
breath. Each day at recess
or gym class, he wakes
up two nights a week
wheezing and doesn't always
get to the end of the month
with each inhaler each
meter dose inhaler comes
with a specific number of
doses enough for two puffs
four times a day for 30
days so he runs out before
that how would you classify
this patient's asthma
this is an asthma
classification table and
this one was taken from
pediatric case files
If you look at it,
asthma is divided
into intermittent
and persistent.
Persistent is further divided
into mild, moderate,
and severe.
The categories are daytime
symptoms, nighttime weakening,
use of short-acting
beta agonists,
interference with
activity, overall lung
function, number of
exacerbations requiring systemic
steroids and therapy.
Our patient fits into
the persistent asthma
in the moderate. So
we would call him moderate
persistent asthma.
Diagnosis and management
for our patient.
How do you diagnose asthma?
You can use spirometry. We
use it in kids that are
age five or older. The five
to seven-year-old group is
difficult to assess because
spirometry, you need to
plug up the nose. They need
to blow out as hard and as
fast as they can, and it's
difficult to get them to
cooperate. So we typically use
clinical signs and symptoms
to diagnose and manage.
And then management
is a stepwise therapy
utilizing multiple drug
classes. Inhaled steroids,
leukotriene modifiers,
long-acting beta-2 agonists,
biologics, monoclonal
antibodies,
short-acting beta agonists,
anticholinergics and
oral corticosteroids.
Mainstay of management
is the avoidance of
triggers and triggers can
include viral infections,
irritants like smoke or
from tobacco or from wood,
dust mites, animal dander,
cockroach, in indoor molds.
This is an example
of the stepwise
approach to treatment.
This was taken
out of the Essentials
of Pediatrics.
This is an asthma action
plan. It comes in triplicate,
one copy for the family
one copy for the chart
and one copy for the school
nurse and what you can
see is it's divided into
green yellow and red zones
it can be read for symptoms
or for peak flow meter
readings and then you write
down everything you want
the patient to do according
to their symptoms let's
go to case number three a
female is born at 38 weeks
gestation from a preemie
gravid first-time pregnant
mom via a spontaneous
vaginal delivery and the
patient is noted to have darkly
stained and foul smelling
amniotic fluid upon
delivery you note low muscle
tone and blueness of the
extremities cyanosis The
APGAR scores are 5 and 6,
taken at 1 and 5 minutes.
APGAR scores are a scoring
system that takes into
account neurologic, cardiac,
and respiratory status of
a newborn. We like to have
APGAR scores of 8 through
10. 10 is the highest. This
patient is compromised.
Neonatal resuscitation is
performed, and the infant
is admitted to the neonatal
intensive care unit.
Physical examination reveals
nasal flaring, grunting,
increased AP diameter,
anterior posterior diameter
of the chest, and
intercostal retractions. The
vital signs, the temperature
is normal, respiratory
rate is elevated, the
heart rate is elevated, the
oxygen saturation is 93%
with O2 binasal cannula. We
have a normal S1 and S2
without murmurs, rubs, or
gallops. And on the respiratory
exam, there's diffuse
ronchi, but no wheezes
and no rails or crackles.
Take a few seconds
and decide what your
diagnosis is. Meconium
aspiration syndrome,
transient tachypnea
of the newborn,
pneumonia, hydrops
vitalis, neonatal
respiratory distress syndrome.
If you chose
meconium aspiration
syndrome, you are correct!
Meconium aspiration syndrome,
M-A-S, meconium. What
is it? It is the bowel
movement of the fetus prior to
delivery and that it typically
occurs when the fetus
is under duress or stress
it's seen in five percent
the syndrome five percent
of all newborns who are
delivered with meconium
staining of the amniotic fluid
then when you have this
bowel movement into
the amniotic fluid prior
to birth then the The
fetus aspirates it into
their lungs, causes
airway obstruction and
respiratory distress.
The x-ray reveals
infiltrates and streaking in
increased anterior-posterior
diameter and flattened
diaphragms. And why does
meconium have an effect
on the lungs? Well, it
causes obstruction and causes
a ball valve effect.
It causes a chemical
irritation. It is a nidus
for infection for bacteria.
And it causes the inhibition of
production and the
function of surfactant.
We often will see
primary pulmonary
hypertension of these
newborns because of the
increased pulmonary
vascular resistance.
This is a hyperlink to
the Merck Manual where
it discusses meconium
aspiration syndrome
in newborns. I think
you'll find it helpful.
How do we manage these
patients? Supportive measures.
If they are febrile, give
them antipyretics. If they're
cold warm them up and
using assisted ventilation.
Surfactin treatment
is sometimes used.
Sometimes we require
the use of antibiotics.
Inhaled nitric oxide
and if all else fails
then ECMO, extracorporeal
membrane oxygenation.
It's a modified
heart-lung apparatus
that allows for
oxygenation of the blood.
Let's see if we can categorize
these respiratory distresses.
So this is newborn
respiratory distress,
differential diagnoses,
not respiratory
distress of the newborn.
We like to separate it
into timing of birth,
either preterm, full
-term, and post-term,
preterm and full-term.
Under preterm, we have
respiratory distress syndrome,
the old-fashioned hyaline
membrane disease, and
apnea of prematurity.
Certainly, if you're not
breathing, you can become
distressed. Full and
post-term, you have primary
pulmonary hypertension
of the neonate, or the
newborn, and meconium
aspiration pneumonia,
as opposed to meconium
aspiration syndrome. We're
doing the differential.
Pre-term and full-term,
you'll see transient
tachypnea of the newborn,
as well as bacterial
sepsis, typically from
group B streptococcus.
how do you evaluate
these patients
chest x-ray you're looking for
parenchymal patterns is
there a pneumothorax what's
the cardiac silhouette
look like an arterial blood
gas for acid-based
disturbances how bad is the
hypercapnia or the hypoxia a
complete blood count. Is the
patient septic? Are they
anemic? Are they in disseminated
intravascular coagulopathy?
A blood culture,
blood glucose, because
hypoglycemia can cause respiratory
distress. Also, you can
have something called
stress hyperglycemia. And
then an echocardiogram,
looking at murmurs or the
pulmonary hypertension,
cardiomegaly, or finding some
structural heart disease.
This is the start of
session two. I am giving a
two-session presentation
and did it in one stream.
Case number four, you can
do this. We're getting
there. This is a four
-month-old infant who
presents to the emergency
department with cough
and runny nose for the
past three days. She
was given acetaminophen
for a tactile fever.
Tactile fever is
when the parents feel
the child and they
say they feel hot.
patient lives at home with
her parents her aunt and
her nine-month-old cousin
the past medical history
is non-contributory and the
family history is positive
for hypertension in grandparents
physical examination
heart rate respiratory
rate and temperature are
elevated and the oxygen
saturation on room air is
decreased at 90 percent. The
patients in mild respiratory
distress with increased
work of breathing noted.
There's clear nasal discharge
with alar flaring. That
means the nares are
flaring out and the rest of
that exam is normal. We have
a regular rhythm with S1
and S2, but no S3, S4, no
murmurs, rubs, or gallops.
There are supraclavicular
retractions, diffuse
wheezing, and crackles heard
throughout all lung fields.
What do you think she
has? Asthma, pneumonia,
bronchiolitis, or
allergic rhinitis?
If you thought bronchiolitis,
you are correct.
Etiology and epidemiology,
the main culprit
is respiratory
syncytial virus, RSV.
But other offenders can
cause bronchiolitis,
human metopneumovirus,
parainfluenza, influenza,
adenovirus, rhinovirus,
and coronavirus. virus.
It usually occurs
in kids two years of
age or younger and
the peak incidence
is between two and
six months of age.
You're at increased risk
if you're premature, you
have chronic lung disease,
congenital heart disease,
neuromuscular weakness,
or immunodeficiency.
In the summer of 2023 the
FDA approved Bayfordis.
This is a monoclonal
antibody injection against
RSV and it's a single
dose and we administer
it during the RSV season
or in preparation of the
season in kids up to 24
months of age if their
moms haven't been
vaccinated during pregnancy.
So it has an incubation
period of about four to
six days, then you have
a three to seven day
window where you progress
to noisy breathing,
wheezing, increased work
of breathing, alar flaring,
intercostal retractions,
pulmonary dysfunction,
and bronchial
hyperreactivity may
persist for several years
after the infection.
What do you look for?
Prolonged exhalation
or expiration,
wheezing, nasal flaring,
suprasternal retractions,
air trapping, and lung
hyperexpansion. When
a patient presents with
grunting and cyanosis,
you know they have
severe disease.
Young infants can present
with apnea, lack of breathing.
This slide just lets
you look at the severity
of the disease over
the course of time,
the signs and symptoms,
the pathophysiology,
and then the histology
of the airway.
Here is an x-ray of an
infant with the diagnosis
of bronchiolitis. The
diaphragms are flat
here and flattened
here. You see there's
retro sternal airspace
from hyperexpansion. You
see that all these
little polka dots here,
inflammation of the airway and
What do we do once we suspect
that this is bronchiolitis?
We monitor with pulse oximetry.
Commonly the pulse
oximeter or the oxygen
saturation is lower
in these kids.
We can do rapid antigen
testing or polymerase
chain reaction PCR to
verify the etiologies
at RSV, parainfluenza,
influenza, adenovirus,
etc. And that can be
done with the nasal swab.
You can get a chest x
-ray. Typically, it's not
needed in the garden
variety bronchiolitis.
But if you did get a
chest x-ray, you'd see
hyperinflation,
flattened diaphragms, and
on the x-ray, if you
see increased densities,
it could be pneumonia
or atelectasis.
You know, earlier in a
case, we had a patient who
was a little older, had
respiratory distress, had
wheezing. Why isn't this
asthma for this patient?
Well,
the presence of fever,
the presence of age,
and the lack, the younger
infant, lack of family history,
lack of past medical
history of atopy, and this
is the first time that
the patient was wheezing.
This table lets you
look at the different
causes of cough and
wheeze in infants
and children and can
be pretty helpful.
How do we treat bronchiolitis?
It's supportive. You give
antipyretics,
adequate hydration,
nasal suctioning, and oxygen
as needed. We typically
do not use bronchodilators,
corticosteroids, or
antibiotics. And while
the mortality rate is low,
it is one to two percent of
all cases here we go case
number five you receive
a call from a colleague
in the emergency department
that your nine-year-old
patient whom you saw in
the fall with the known
history of asthma has
presented again this time with
fever cough and chills you
go to the ed to see for
yourself. General, he's
ill-appearing, pale, and
diaphoretic with an audible
wet cough. He has an elevated
temperature at 102.5 degrees
Fahrenheit. His heart
rate is elevated at 110. His
respiratory rate is elevated
at 32 breaths per minute.
Blood pressure is 116
over 82. Cardio exam, S1 and
S2 with no murmurs rubs or
gallops his capillary
refill is delayed at greater
than two seconds on the
respiratory exam he's using
accessory muscles to breathe
he has bronchophony in the
right lower lobe with
dullness to percussion in that
area breath sounds are
heard in all lung fields but
he has a prolonged expiratory
phase with wheezes and
crackles and ronchi heard
over that right lower lobe.
Here is your chest x-ray
and if you notice right
on the right lower lobe
is whiter than on the left
lower lobe.
what do you think your
patient has it's still
asthma laryngitis
pneumothorax or pneumonia
if you answered
pneumonia you are correct
epidemiology of pneumonia
well we've reduced the
incidence of pneumonia specifically
because of the development
of vaccines and success
of vaccination programs.
Pertussis, diphtheria,
measles, haemophilus
influenzae type B,
strep pneumoniae, which is
pneumococcus, influenza,
and COVID.
Even with these vaccines,
there are still 1
million children who
die each year worldwide
under the age of five,
which is pretty sad.
What are the risk factors
for developing pneumonia?
Gastroesophageal reflux.
If you have acidic
contents from the stomach
refluxing up the esophagus
and into the lungs, it causes
a chemical pneumonitis,
which is a for bacterial
and viral growth.
Neurologic impairment, if you
don't have a strong
cough reflex,
or the ability to
cough, you can't cough
out irritants,
bacteria, viruses, etc.
And then they start to
grow and cause pneumonia.
Immunocompromised individuals,
they can't fight the infection.
Anatomic abnormalities
that get in the way
of secretion clearance
and the ability to
prevent contents from
entering the lungs.
group home environment
because of the close
contact with others and
the increased incidence
of illnesses infectious
diseases as well as
hospitalization same
sort of thing sick people
in the hospital pass
those germs around and you
are increased risk for
developing pneumonia
What are the
clinical distinctions
between viral and
bacterial pneumonia?
On the left side
lists the viral
components. There's
cough, wheeze, stridor.
There may be fever, but
it's a lower grade fever.
And typically there's
upper respiratory mucosal
congestion and inflammation.
The chest x-ray will show
diffuse infiltrates and
hyperaeration, as opposed
to on the bacterial side,
it's a high fever, chills,
cough,
dyspnea, difficulty breathing,
consolidation on
your auscultory exam,
dullness to
percussion, and on the
chest x-ray, low
bar consolidation.
let's take a look at
the breakdown of the
microbiology by age group
so for newborn infants
that's less than a month of
age most common pathogens
group b strep e coli
gram negative bacilli
and some strep pneumoniae
one to three months
of age if they're febrile
rsv and other viruses,
if they're afebrile,
chlamydia trachomatis,
amhominis and CMV
pertussis. Three to five,
three months to five
years of age, we
have RSV and the other
respiratory viruses,
strep pneumo, and
haemophilus influenza.
The five to 18 year old
group mycoplasma pneumoniae
is the most common along
with strep pneumonia
and C pneumonia and then
greater than 18 years
of age mycoplasma pneumonia
strep pneumonia in
H influenza influenza
adenovirus and C pneumonia
how do you manage these
patients well you have to
listen to the history
perform the physical exam
perform imaging if necessary,
and take into account
the patient's age. That's
what will direct the care.
We typically identify
an organism 40 to 80
percent of the time.
In hospitalized patients,
it's more important because
you may have certain
resistant organisms in the
hospitalized patient,
the hospitalized patient
tends to be sicker, so it's
a little more urgent that
we find out the actual
cause. In the outpatient
setting, we go by past
data and make assumptions.
You can perform a thoracentesis,
which can be diagnostic
and therapeutic if there's
an embiema or pleural
effusion, and then
surgical management may be
necessary for abscesses, a
pneumatocele, or an empyema.
In our particular
patient, pneumonia can
trigger a new asthmatic
episode and asthma can
predispose a patient
to getting pneumonia.
Case number six, a previously
healthy two-year-old
is brought to the emergency
department with a two-hour
history of fever and
harsh breathing while she
inhales, according to her
mother. There are no known
sick contacts or witnessed
episodes of choking, and
per the parent's wishes,
the patient is unimmunized.
She has a hoarse cry,
an inspiratory stridor,
suprasternal retractions,
going in like,
like this, and she appears
toxic. Her temperature
is elevated at 102
degrees Fahrenheit.
Heart rate is elevated
at 150 beats per minute.
Respiratory rate is
elevated at 40 breaths per
minute, and her oxygen
saturation is 97% on room
air. Her respiratory exam
has high-pitched noise
over the trachea on
inspiration. Lungs are clear to
auscultation bilaterally
without any wheezes,
rails or bronchi, and her
heart exam, normal S1,
S2, with no S3, S4, no
murmurs, rubs, or gallops.
What do you think is the
most likely diagnosis?
Epiglottitis,
retropharyngeal abscess,
laryngotracheobronchitis,
also known as croup,
peritonsillar abscess,
or bacterial tracheitis.
If you chose epiglottitis,
then you are correct.
This is a lateral neck
film, and we rarely shoot
these films prior to
stabilizing the airway, because
we don't want to move
these kids or upset them.
The epiglottis can then
totally block the airway, and
that's not good, too. this
is the lateral neck film
where the arrow is pointing
is the swollen epiglottis
if you turn your thumb
sideways you get this look
this is weird for me and
the camera to do to get a
look like that and that's
called a thumb sign well
the etiology of epiglottitis
the most common bacterial
causes. Number one is
group A streptococcus, then
staph aureus, then haemophilus
influenza type B in the
unimmunized or under
immunized. The radiograph, like
we talked about before,
has this thumb sign, which
is the inflamed epiglottis.
How do you diagnose it?
It's direct visualization
as you're placing the et
tube the endotracheal tube
the management you want a
calm quiet environment you
need to secure the airway
and treat with iv antibiotics
and steroids so this
is typically where the child
will be placed in a quiet
area of the emergency room
everything is very calm
then we will take
them to the or where
the lights are dim
and keep things
under a very calm
controlled situation.
We learn about epiglottitis
in the pediatric population
but guess what? It
happens in adults too and
this comes from a 2019 New
England Journal of Medicine
article and here you see
the lateral neck film
with the arrow pointing to
that thumb sign and then
you look at B which is
the laryngoscopy and they
did it in the emergency
room. You see how swollen
the epiglottis is and it's
friable and disgusting.
And then picture C
is five days of IV
antibiotics and 14 days
of oral amoxicillin and
clavulanic acid and it
goes back to normal.
Pretty awful.
Strider is a noise. It's
not a diagnosis. So it's a
noise that's made from
inflammation of an airway.
And it can be caused by a
variety of reasons. One is
retropharyngeal abscess,
foreign body aspiration,
laryngotracheobronchitis,
which is, we know it as croup,
a peritonsillar abscess, and
that's in figure
35-4, just below,
an airway hemangioma,
subglottic stenosis that used to
occur with greater frequency
when we intubated premature
infants for a long period
of time. Inflammation and
scar tissue would build up
and vocal cord paralysis.
On the right-hand
side, we go back to
anatomy and looking
at the deep cervical
fascia and where these
different fascial
layers can have infection
and inflammation.
We have made it to the summary
slide, so congratulations.
epiglottitis it's often
vaccine preventable it's
an inflammation of the
epiglottis and that's what
you can see if you obtain
a lateral neck film we
typically diagnose from
clinical signs and physical
examination which helps
us differentiate it from
other causes of respiratory
distress Pneumonia.
Age groups are important,
the age of the patient. It
helps us predict the etiology.
It guides our treatment,
helps us distinguish between
viral and bacterial, and
we go by clinical and x-ray
patterns are different for
the different offenders,
causes of pneumonia.
Bronchiolitis, it's usually
caused by respiratory syncytial
virus, but remember other
viruses can cause it. It peaks
out at two to six months
of age, and we do have
monoclonal antibody therapy
that is recommended for infants
during the RSV season to
help decrease the devastation
that bronchiolitis can
cause. Meconium aspiration
syndrome, that has multiple
effects on the lungs and it
is different from other
newborn respiratory distress
causes. Asthma, it's reversible.
It's episodic. You may
need maintenance therapy
and there are many triggers.
Cystic fibrosis, multiple
genetic mutations.
The gold standard
is sweat chloride
testing. It's a multi
-organ involvement. It's
chronic, but the
lifespan is improving.
This concludes our pediatric
respiratory presentation.
This is the hyperlink to
filling out the survey.
Remember, I am available.
Reach out to me. We can chat
on the phone, via Zoom, stop
by my office, correspond
by email. Please don't
hesitate to reach out.
Be well, everyone.